<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christian religious meetings allowed by liturgie are no seditious conventicles, nor punishable by the late act, or, What persons and meetings are owned and allowed by the liturgie of the Church of England and also, what makes a religious meeting to pass and suffer under the name of a seditious conventicle, and likewise, what is a conventicle and what is not a conventicle ... / written the beginning of the fourth moneth in the year 1664 by R.F.</title>
            <author>R. F. (Richard Farnworth), d. 1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1664</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40928</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F476</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25391</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08944421</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08944421</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42053</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40928)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42053)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1283:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christian religious meetings allowed by liturgie are no seditious conventicles, nor punishable by the late act, or, What persons and meetings are owned and allowed by the liturgie of the Church of England and also, what makes a religious meeting to pass and suffer under the name of a seditious conventicle, and likewise, what is a conventicle and what is not a conventicle ... / written the beginning of the fourth moneth in the year 1664 by R.F.</title>
                  <author>R. F. (Richard Farnworth), d. 1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1664]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>Assembly, Right of --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42053:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42053:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Chriſtian Religious Meetings Allowed by the Liturgie, Are no Seditious Conventicles, nor puniſhable by the late Act.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OR,</hi> What Perſons and Meetings are Owned and Allowed by the Liturgie of the Church of <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And alſo, What makes a Religious Meeting to paſs and Suffer under the Name of a Seditious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticle. And likewiſe, what is a Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, and what is not a Conventicle. And concerning the Church and its Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And the Difference between obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately and Conſcientiouſly refuſing to take Judicial Oaths. And concerning the Jurors and Judges, who may be concerned to hear and determine the Cauſes and Matters aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Written the beginning of the fourth Moneth, in the Year 1664. By <hi>R. F.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:42053:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42053:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:42053:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:42053:3"/>
            <head>Chriſtian Religious Meetings allowed by the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgie, are no Seditious Conventicles, nor pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhable by the Late Act, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>WHereas by the Act, Entituled, <hi>An Act to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent and ſuppreſs Seditious Conventicles,</hi> It is Enacted and Declared, That <hi>if any Perſon of the Age of ſixteen years, or upwards, being a Subject of this Realm, at any time after the firſt day of July, which ſhall be in the Year of our Lord God</hi> 1664. <hi>ſhall be preſent at any Aſſembly, Conventicle, or Meeting, under colour or pretence of any Exerciſe of Religion, in other manner than is allowed by the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy, or practiſe of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>at which Meeting or Aſſembly, there ſhall be five perſons, or more, aſſembled together, over and above thoſe of the ſame Houſhold; Then it ſhall and may be lawful for two Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of Peace to commit them to Priſon, &amp;c. for the firſt and ſecond Offence, in Order to Tranſportation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is not this a matter very diſputable, and doth it not belong to ſpiritual men to judg, what Meetings upon the account of Religion do agree with, or are contrary to the Liturgie or practiſe of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> before the penalties of the Act be put in execution againſt them?</p>
            <p>For if to aſſemble and meet together upon the account of Religion, according to Scripture, be to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble and meet together according to the Liturgie and practiſe of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> then they who aſſemble and meet together upon the account
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:42053:4"/>of Religion and Worſhip of God according to the Scripture (to the number of five or upwards) they do not meet contrary to the allowance of the Liturgie, or practiſe of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>If the Liturgy do allow of meeting together, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Scripture, then they who meet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether according to the Scriptures, are no ſeditious Sectaries, neither is their Religious meetings ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Conventicles, or puniſhable by the ſaid Act, being according to Scripture, and allowed of by the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgie of the Church, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>The Liturgie allows of the Scripture as its foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation,<note place="margin">The Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture is owned as the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap> of the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, &amp;c.</note> and the Scriptures are acknowledged by the Liturgy to be the moving cauſe of peoples Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Acknowledgment unto God of their mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold ſins and tranſgreſſions, with an humble, lowly, penitent and obedient heart, to the end that they may receive forgiveneſs of the ſame by his infinite goodneſs and mercy; for proof thereof ſee the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the Liturgy.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">What the Liturgie alloweth at Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</note>To aſſemble and meet together before the Lord to render thanks for the great benefits that we have received at his hands, to ſet forth his moſt worthy praiſe, to hear his moſt holy Word, and to ask thoſe things which be requiſite and neceſſary, as well for the Body as the Soul, and to accompany one another in prayer, with a pure heart and an humble voyce, to the Throne of Gods heavenly Grace, is that which the Liturgie owns and allows of, as its own and the Churches Practiſe; ſee for pro of thereof that part of the Liturgy at the beginning, where it is ſaid,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:42053:4"/>
               <hi>Dearly Beloved Brethren, the Scripture moveth us in ſundry places, to acknowledge and confeſs our mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold ſins and tranſgreſſions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">To meet according to the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy.</note>Seeing it is ſo; Then for us and the People of God to aſſemble and meet together (to the number of five and above) before the Lord, upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of Religion, as Worſhippers of him, to render thanks for the great benefit we have received at his hands, to ſet forth his moſt worthy praiſe, to hear his moſt holy Word, and to ask thoſe things which be requiſite and neceſſary, as well for the Body, as the Soul, and to accompany one another in prayer, with a pure heart and an humble voyce, to the Throne of Gods heavenly Grace, is allowed by the Liturgie,<note place="margin">Meetings not pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhable by the late Act; but freed from the penalties, being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, &amp;c.</note> and according to the practiſe of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> And therefore ſuch ought not to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, but acquitted and tolerated, who aſſemble and meet according to the Liturgie, or practiſe of the Church, as aforeſaid; becauſe ſuch their godly religious meetings are allowed by the Liturgy of the Church, and ſuch meetings are not prohibited but allowed by the Act, as are allowed by the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy or practiſe of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By what hath been ſaid, it may and doth appear what the Liturgie of the Church of <hi>England</hi> is,<note place="margin">How can evidence or Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be ſafely giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en without danger in ſuch caſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> and what it doth allow, and that our godly and religious Meetings are not contrary to the allowance of the Liturgie or practiſe of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as aforeſaid: How can they then that come to ſwear againſt us, ſwear with a ſafe Conſcience, that we meet and aſſemble together on the behalf of the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:42053:5"/>Lord as his Worſhippers, contrary to the allowance of the Liturgie, or practiſe of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> And if our Jurors or Judges be not ſpiritual men, and underſtanding in Divine matters, how will they judge aright in this caſe? that they may not deſtroy, but preſerve us in our Liberties, Principles, and Practiſes.</p>
            <p>Seeing that in this Caſe much ambiguity or doubt may ariſe, and if this be a Spiritual cauſe, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine matter, which is to be heard and determined, that is to ſay, Whether we meet and aſſemble toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on the behalf of the Lord, as his Worſhippers, or no; And whether ſuch our godly and religious meetings, be contrary to, or agreeable to what the Liturgie or practiſe of the Church of <hi>England</hi> in ſuch caſes alloweth of; ought not we herein to be judged by Spiritual men? Becauſe it is ſaid in the Statute of the 24 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>That the Body Spiritual having power,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>Chap.</hi> 12.</note> 
               <hi>when any Cauſe of the Law Divine hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens to come in queſtion, or of Spiritual Learning, to declare and determine all ſuch doubts, and to admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter all ſuch Offices and Duties, as to the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r Room Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual doth appertain; for the due adminiſtration whereof, and to keep them from corruption, and ſini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter affection, the Kings moſt noble Progenitors, and the Anceſtors of the Nobles of this Realm, have ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently endowed them with honour and Poſſeſſions. And the Laws temporal are for Tryal of Property of Lands and Goods and for the Conſervation of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of this Realm in unity and peace, without Ravin or Spoyl, by the Temporal Judges, and the other by the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:42053:5"/>Spiritual Judges, as aforeſaid, or as by the ſaid Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute may be ſeen,</hi> 24 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.12.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Seditious Conventicles.</head>
               <p>ANd as concerning ſeditious Conventicles, provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt by the Act,<note place="margin">The reaſon given for preventing and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing ſeditious Conventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, &amp;c.</note> and the Reaſon given for the preventing and ſuppreſſing of them, It is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in the Preamble or Ground of the Act, the Reaſon for making the Act, which is, <hi>viz. For pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding therefore of further and more ſpeedy Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies againſt the gro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing and dangerous practiſes of ſeditious Sectaries, and other diſloyal perſons, who under pretence of tender Conſciences, do at their Meetings contrive Inſurrections, as late experience hath ſhewed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Seditious Sectaries who at their meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings do contrive Inſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ought to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, &amp; Remedies againſt ſuch meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to be provided. The inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> free from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triving In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons at their god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, as experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence hath ſhewed.</note>Are not thoſe perſons and that people only decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to be ſeditious Sectaries and diſloyal perſons, who under pretence of tender Conſciences, do at their Meetings contrive Inſurrections? as late expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience hath ſhewed: And may they not juſtly be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to be ſo, who are ſo indeed? for there is good reaſon to provide Remedies againſt ſuch perſons and practiſes, who under pretence of tenderneſs of Conſcience, do at their Meetings contrive Inſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>But as concerning the innocent people of God, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachfully called <hi>Quakers,</hi> they are clear and free from ſuch ſeditious and dangerous practiſes, and are not thoſe ſeditious Sectaries and diſloyal perſons, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:42053:6"/>cauſe they neither have, nor do at their Meetings contrive Inſurrections, neither hath former or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent experience ſhewed any ſuch thing to be done, or intended by them; for it is againſt their Principles, practiſes, doctrines, and judgments, and they are ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly and abſolutely againſt deſigning or contriving any ſuch things; neither did their godly Religious Meetings ever produce any ſuch bad effects, as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience hath ſhewed for many years by-paſt.</p>
               <p>What is a Conventicle according to the Act, and puniſhable by the ſame accordingly? ought not this to be known and rightly conſidered by them that are to be Witneſſes, Jurors, or Judges, that the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent may not be condemned with the wicked, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is forbidden by the Law of God, ſaying, <hi>The Innocent and Righteous ſlay thou not;</hi> therefore by the Law of God, the Innocent and Righteous are not to be deſtroyed, but preſerved in their Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and Practiſes, to God-wards, as well as in their Liberties, Perſons, and Eſtates.</p>
               <p>To meet together in a private Houſe, to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of four,<note place="margin">what is not a <hi>Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle.</hi>
                  </note> beſides the Houſhold or Family, is no ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious Conventicle, neither is ſuch private Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings either declared by the ſaid Act to be ſuch Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticles, neither are they provided againſt by the ſaid Act, or puniſhable thereby, but juſtified and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerated, and not at all condemned. Therefore private Meetings, or to meet in private Houſes, to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of four beſide the Houſhold or Family, are no ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious Conventicles, though they may meet contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Liturgie, or practiſe of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:42053:6"/>And (it ſeems) according to the intent of the Act, to meet and aſſemble together to the number of five or upwards, beſides them of the Houſhold or Family where they do meet, under colour or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of any exerciſe of Religion, in other manner than is allowed by the Liturgie, or practiſe of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> is an offence.</p>
               <p>Then, it ſeems, to meet together in greater or leſſer numbers, upon the account of Religion, ſo that they who aſſemble and meet together for the Exerciſe of Religion, do preach and pray, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form Religious Exerciſe and Duty to God, allowed by the Liturgie or practiſe of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> is no offence.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">What god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings are, according unto, or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c.</note>What is it then for a people to meet in greater Numbers (than four, beſides the Houſhold or Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily) upon the Account of Religious Exerciſes, and not to be contrary unto, but allowed of by the Liturgie, or practiſe of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> ſo as ſuch Religious Meetings may not ſuffer by the Late Act? To the which, ſomthing is ſaid before, that to Aſſemble and Meet together (to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of five, or above) before the Lord, upon the account of Religion, as Worſhippers of him, to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thanks unto God for the great benefits that we have received of him, to ſet forth his moſt worthy praiſe, to hear his moſt holy Word, and to ask thoſe things which be requiſite and neceſſary both for Soul and Body, and in the performance of that Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to accompany one another in Prayer, with a pure Heart, and an humble Voyce, to the Throne of Gods
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:42053:7"/>Heavenly Grace, is allowed by the Liturgie and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>To Aſſemble and Meet together before the Lord upon the account of Religion and Worſhip, to Preach and Pray, or perform Duty to God, is not contrary unto, but allowed of by the Liturgie, and is according to the practiſe of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> becauſe they either do, or ought ſo to do, as aforeſaid; and we meet together before the Lord, as Worſhippers of him, to Preach and Pray, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form Duty to God, therefore our Meetings are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the practiſe of the Church, and allowed of by the Liturgie, as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>Again, The Liturgie of the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">See Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion upon the Feaſt of Trinity ſo called.</note> 
                  <hi>It is very meet, right, and our bounden Duty, that we ſhould at all times, and in all places, perform Duty to God:</hi> And if it be very meet, right, and the bounden Duty of a profeſſing people, that they ſhould at all times, and in all places, meet together to Worſhip God, or perform Duty unto him, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, then for us, and the people of the Lord to meet together at any time, and in any place, to Worſhip God, or perform Duty unto him as his people, or true Worſhippers of him, is not contrary unto, but accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the manner that is allowed of by the Liturgie of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">See Good Friday, the Collects ſo called.</note>The Church is declared by the Liturgie <hi>to be the Houſhold and Family of God;</hi> then they who are of Gods Houſhold and Family, may meet and aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble together to wait upon God in the way of his worſhip: and not go under the name of ſeditious
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:42053:7"/>Conventicles, becauſe the Liturgie declareth the Church to be the Houſhold and Family of God, and Pariſh Meeting places are not that Houſhold and Family, neither are wicked unſanctified people the Houſhold and Family of God: Therefore wicked unſanctified people are not allowed of by the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, or declared to be the Church of God; and to refuſe to meet in point of Religion and Worſhip with ſuch as are not of Gods Houſhold and Family, is not to refuſe to come to the Church and Service of God; but to aſſemble and meet together in point of Religion and Worſhip of God, with the Houſhold and Family of God, to perform Duty un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him at any time, and in any place, is to come to the Church and Service of God, according to the allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the Liturgie of the Church, as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">What is owned by the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie to be a Church, what is not.</note>That the Church is not owned or declared by the Liturgie to be either the Pariſh Meeting places, or wicked unſanctified perſons, though they may aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and meet there, is very plain; becauſe the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie declareth and ſaith, the Church either are, or ſhould be <hi>Regenerated and Born of God;</hi> and they who are not Regenerate and Born of God, are not owned or declared by the Liturgie to be any Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> And again, the Church is declared by the Liturgie, not only to be Regenerate and Born of Water and the Spirit, but it is alſo Declared by the Liturgie, <hi>that the whole Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the Church is governed and ſanctified by the Spirit of God;</hi> for proof thereof,<note place="margin">Order of Baptiſm. Good Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day Col.</note> ſee that called the Order of Baptiſm, and on Good Friday the Collects.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:42053:8"/>
                  <note place="margin">Admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance into Church-Fellowſhip and becom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>urch members, according to the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgie.</note>Seeing then it remains true, according to the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgie, that none are admitted into Church Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, nor accounted Church-Members, but ſuch as are Regenerate and Born of God, and they who are Governed and Sanctified by the Spirit of God: Then to aſſemble and meet together with ſuch as are born of God, and Governed and Sanctified by the Spirit of God, is not contrary unto, but according to the manner allowed of by the Liturgie of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Church is Spiritual according to the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgie.</note>If the whole Body of the Church be Governed and Sanctified by the Spirit of God, then every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Member thereof is under the Government and Sanctification of the Spirit of God, as aforeſaid; and it ſeems ſuch are the only Church Members al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by the Liturgie of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> then they who have the ſenſe and knowledg of the Work of Gods Spirit upon their hearts,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11 <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.6, 7. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.10, 11, 12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.14, 15, 16, 17.</note> and working within them, both for Regeneration, Government of heart, and Sanctification, and alſo teſtifying unto their ſpirits, that they are the children of God, as the Saints and Believers in Chriſt aforetime had, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Scripture Record, thoſe are the true Church, and they and their Meetings are allowed of by the Liturgie aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>Then they who are not governed and ſanctified by the Spirit of God,<note place="margin">Who are owned to be Mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Members of the Church, and who are not, both accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Liturgie and Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> are no Miniſters, nor Members of the Church, neither according to the Liturgie, nor the Scriptures. For the Liturgie ſaith, the whole Body of the Church is governed and ſanctified by the Spirit of God; then they who are not govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:42053:8"/>and ſanctified by the Spirit of God, are not owned either as Miniſters or Members of the Church; and the Scripture ſaith, <hi>If any man have not the Spirit of Chriſt, he is none of his:</hi> Chriſt doth not own any, either as his Miniſters, or Members of his Church, if they have not his Spirit, as aforeſaid. See <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.9.</p>
               <p>Seeing that the whole Body of the Church is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by the Liturgie to be Governed and Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Spirit of God, is not the body of the Church a ſanctified Body, and under a ſpiritual Government? And ought not Spiritual men to hear and determine ſpiritual matters? And ſeeing that it is a ſpiritual matter that is like to come in queſtion, about meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing according to the allowance of the Liturgie, or no, may not thoſe that are to be tryed in ſuch caſes, juſtly appeal to the ſpiritual Judges, to judg of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Cauſes, and not to the Temporal Judges; for is there not belonging unto the Imperial Crown of the Realm, a Body Politick, compact of all ſorts and degrees of people, divided in Terms and by Names of Spirituality and Temporality, to render and yield Juſtice and final determination to all manner of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, reſiants or ſubjects within the Kings Realm, in all Cauſes, Matters, Debates, and contentions hapning to occur, inſurge, or begin with the limits thereof? And hath not the Body Spiritual power, when any Cauſe of the Law Divine hapneth to come in queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or of Spiritual Learning, to declare and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine all ſuch doubts? and are not the Laws Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral for Tryal of Property of Lands and Goods,<note place="margin">24 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>Chap.</hi> 12.</note> and for the Conſervation of the people of this Realm in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:42053:9"/>unity and peace, without Ravin or ſpoyl. And are not thoſe Temporal Laws to be adminiſtred and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted by ſundry Judges and Miniſters of the other part of the ſaid Body Politick, called the Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality? If the Body Politick be divided into, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt of two Parts, the one part called by the name of Spirituality, and the other part called the Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality; the one to hear and determine ſpiritual mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and cauſes and the other to hear and determine Temporal cauſes and matters: For as much as ours is a ſpiritual matter or cauſe, being concerning the Worſhip of God, ought not the Temporal Judges to leave it to the ſpiritual Judges to hear and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine? The whole ſtreſs of the matter lyeth in this thing, that is to ſay, whether Meetings upon the account of Religion be allowed by the Liturgie or practiſe of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> or no? For thoſe Meetings that are not contrary to the allowance of the Liturgie or practice of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> are not (it ſeems) neither prohibited, nor puniſhable by the Act, as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>It is declared by the Liturgie of the Church of <hi>England,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Coll.</hi> for Peace.</note> 
                  <hi>that the Service of God is perfect freedome;</hi> and ſeeing that by the Liturgie of the Church of <hi>England</hi> the ſervice of God is owned, allowed of, and declared to be perfect freedom, whether ought any perſon or perſons whatſoever, to be forced either to it or from it by outward compulſion, but rather left to their liberty and freedom concerning the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:42053:9"/>
               <head>Concerning Oaths, and Jurors, or Judges, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>WHereas it is ſaid in the late Act, <hi>That there are ſome perſons that do obſtruct the proceeding of Juſtice by their obſtinate refuſal to take Oaths law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully tendred unto them in the ordinary courſe of Law; It is enacted, That if any perſons do refuſe to take a judicial Oath in any Court of Record, except Court Leets, being duly and legally ſummoned, or ſerved with proceſs to appear in ſuch Courts, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, as a witneſs, or returned to ſerve of any Jury, or ordered to be examined upon Interrogatories, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no Legal Plea, to juſtifie or excuſe the refuſal of the ſame Oath; or if any perſons be duly ſerved with a Proceſs, to anſwer any Bill exhibited againſt them, in any Court of Equity, or any ſuit in any Court Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſhall refuſe to anſwer ſuch Bill or Suit up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Oath, in caſes where the Law requires ſuch anſwer to be upon Oath, or be ſummoned to be a Witneſs in any ſuch Court, or ordered to be examined upon Interro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatories, ſhall for any Cauſe or Reaſon not allowed by Law, refuſe to take ſuch Oath, that then for every ſuch offence, as aforeſaid, they ſhall incur the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and puniſhment of Tranſportation,</hi> as is appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the ſaid Act.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Obſtinate refuſing of Oaths.</note>If thoſe who obſtinately do refuſe to take Judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Oaths, be the only perſons that obſtruct the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding of Juſtice by their obſtinate refuſal ſo to do, without ſhewing any good reaſon for their refuſal, be the only perſons intended, and againſt whom
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:42053:10"/>the penalties of the Act in ſuch caſes are to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended. Then they who out of Conſcience to God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards do refuſe to take Oaths, and by giving a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon wherefore they cannot ſwear or take Oaths, as aforeſaid, do make it appear (to the witneſs of God in the Conſciences of men) that their ſo refuſing to ſwear, is not out of obſtinacy, but out of Conſcience to Godward, as aforeſaid; ought not they to be ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly dealt with, and freed from the ſeverity of the ſaid Act in thoſe Caſes of Conſcience?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Difference between obſtinately ly and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly refuſing to ſwear.</note>For there is a great difference between obſtinate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly refuſing to ſwear, and conſcientiouſly to refuſe to take Oaths; and if they who obſtinately, without ſhewing any reaſon, refuſe to take Judicial Oaths, as aforeſaid, be the only Obſtructers of Juſtice by their obſtinacy, and the perſons puniſhable by the ſaid Act in ſuch caſes; then they who do not obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately, but conſcientiouſly refuſe, who out of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to Godward dare not take an Oath, they are not concern'd therein, but ought to be clear and free from the ſame.</p>
               <p>Is it not well known after many years experience &amp; tryal, that God hath an innocent people reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully called <hi>Quakers</hi> in this King dom, who do not obſtinately, but out of Conſcience, refuſe to take Oaths? It is matter of Conſcience to them not to ſwear at all, becauſe Chriſt Jeſus the Prince of the Kings of the Earth doth forbid it,<note place="margin">Rev. 1.5. Mat. 5.34.</note> ſaying to his friends &amp; ſubjects <hi>Swear not at all.</hi> But if any whoſe principle, judgment, and faith, is to ſwear and take Oaths, ſhould obſtinately, without ſhewing a lawful
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:42053:10"/>reaſon, refuſe to take Judicial Oaths, to obſtruct the proceeding of Juſtice by their obſtinacy, it is good to provide againſt ſuch, and to diſtinguiſh between them who obſtinately refuſe to ſwear, and they who conſcientiouſly refuſe to take Oaths; that they who out of Conſcience to Godwards dare not ſwear and take Oaths, may go unpuniſhed for ſuch a refuſal: And would it not be a good thing to provide Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies for tender Conſciences, how to take their Teſtimonies without Oath, whoſe word and promiſe is as obligatory and binding to them, as Oath or Bond can be?</p>
               <p>They who in obedience to the Will of God, and Command of Chriſt Jeſus, under the Covenant of Grace, do refuſe to ſwear &amp; take Oaths in one caſe or other, ſuch do not obſtinately,<note place="margin">Mat 5.34.</note> but conſcientiouſly refuſe to take Oaths, and they have a good reaſon in Law, or a lawful plea (in the ſight of the Lord,<note place="margin">Lam 5.12.</note> and accepted of by him) to juſtifie and excuſe their refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal of Oaths, and ſuch perſons ought to be tenderly dealt withal; and ought they not alſo to be clearly acquitted or freed from the force of the penalties?</p>
               <p>For they who out of tenderneſs of Conſcience cannot take any Oaths, they have the command of Chriſt Jeſus under the Goſpel (whereby he repealed Oaths under the Law) to plead for their excuſe and juſtification; and what a better plea,<note place="margin">Mat. 5.33, 34, 35, 36, 37.</note> more lawful and reaſonable, can in ſuch a caſe be produced and brought forth, as a reaſon of a conſcientious refuſal of Oaths? It is accepted and taken by the great God of Heaven, and why ſhould it be refuſed by men?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:42053:11"/>It is accounted unlawful now in this age for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians (Saints &amp; Believers in Chriſt the Commander) to obey the Will of God, and Command of Chriſt Jeſus? If not, Then is it not (now accounted) lawful and reaſonable (in Law) to obey the Will of God and Command of Chriſt Jeſus, the Prince of the Kings of the Earth, and to plead his command under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, as their juſtification for not ſwearing; becauſe he ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all, neither by Heaven nor earth</hi> (and therefore not by things therein contained) ſo that it is the duty of Chriſtians to be obedient unto Chriſt Jeſus, who commands his Diſciples and Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers to be true and faithful unto him, by denying all Swearing, and to ſpeak Truth (which is the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance or end of an Oath) upon every occaſion.</p>
               <p>And ought not this plea to be owned, accepted, and taken in Law, and by the Jurors, or Judges, as a ſufficient reaſon in Law, to juſtifie or excuſe the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious refuſal of Oaths, by them who do not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinately, but out of Conſcience refuſe to take Oaths? And is it not the Duty of Jurors, or Judges (to God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards) to accept and allow of the ſame to be good and ſufficient (in Law) to all intents, conſtructions, and purpoſes, in the caſes aforeſaid? becauſe the Law of God is ſaid to be the ground of the Law of the Land, and that all Laws ought to be conſonant to the Law of God: and therefore it is ſaid (in the Book called <hi>Doct. and Student, Chap.</hi> 6.) <hi>The ſecond Ground of the Law of England, is the Law of God:</hi> and alſo, <hi>If any general Cuſtome were directly againſt the Law of God, or if any Statute were made directly
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:42053:11"/>againſt it, the Cuſtome and Statute were voyd.</hi> Doct. and Stud. <hi>cap.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>And again, though that be a good reaſon to plead againſt ſwearing, becauſe Chriſt Jeſus under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel commands the contrary; and ſeeing that ſuch a Plea God accepts, why ſhould it not be accepted and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llowed by men, who may be our Jurors and Judges? And moreover, becauſe the Jurors and Judges, and both we and many other Proteſtants have covenant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with God by promiſe and vows, Firſt,<note place="margin">See that called the Order of Bap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>m.</note> to forſake the Devil and all his works; and Secondly, to keep Gods holy Will and Commandments, and walk in the ſame all the dayes of our lives: and ſeeing that ſwearing is againſt the Will of God under the New Covenant and Goſpel Diſpenſation, being contrary to the Command of Chriſt Jeſus, who ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all;</hi> have not both Jurors and Judges,<note place="margin">Mat. 5 34. Jam. 5 12.</note> and we and many good Proteſtants covenanted with God by promiſe and vow, againſt Swearing, as aforeſaid? Conſider well of it.</p>
               <p>And likewiſe, if it be asked of us, why we refuſe to ſwear and take Oaths, may it not be truly anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and pleaded, that we cannot ſwear &amp; take Oaths, becauſe the Biſhops and Prieſts have bound us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a ſolemn Vow againſt Oaths, by cauſing us to covenant with God by promiſe and vow, in order to the obtaining that honourable Title of Chriſtians, <hi>&amp;c. to forſake the Devil and all his works, and to keep Gods holy Will and Commandments all the dayes of our lives;</hi> and doth it not plainly appear, that Swearing under the Goſpel Diſpenſation is againſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:42053:12"/>the Will of God, being contrary to the command of Chriſt Jeſus, as aſoreſaid.</p>
               <p>And we make Conſcience of it, it is great matter of Conſcience to us, both to keep Covenant with God, and alſo to keep the command of Chriſt Jeſus; and if you or any can convince us, that we may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully break Covenant with God, and diſobey the Command of Chriſt Jeſus, without incurring the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure of God, and violating the Fundamentals of the Epiſcopal and Proteſtant Religion, we ſhall hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to you, and take it into due conſideration.</p>
               <p>And moreover, many of the friends of Chriſt Jeſus are excommunicated (as Chriſt hath foretold in his Propheſie <hi>John</hi> 16.) and doth not that Act of Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication put them out of a Legal capacity of tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Judicial Oath,<note place="margin">John 16.1, 2, 3.</note> or bearing an Office? And if ſo, may not that be pleaded and taken as a Legal plea, to juſtifie or excuſe ſuch for refuſing of Oaths?</p>
               <p>And if Swearing before a Magiſtrate be lookt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be of Divine Inſtitution, and according to the appointment of God, where doth or can it be made apparent by any plain Text of Scripture, that God ordained and appointed one Magiſtrate to admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter an Oath to another, before he could be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into his Office; and that an Oath was ordained and appointed of God, to be adminiſtred to a third perſon by a Magiſtrate, for the deciſion of a Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie? and if that can be proved by Scripture, it may be of great ſatisfaction: and if not, Ought not tender hearted people to be freed from the impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Oaths upon their Conſciences in the caſes aforeſaid?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:42053:12"/>And for that, and the cauſes and reaſons aforeſaid, Ought not the Jurors and Judges to be tender to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the people of God reproachfully called <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> and to acquit them from the penalties provid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Act againſt Meeting and Swearing? Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider well of it in Chriſtian Moderation and the fear of the Lord, and the Lord guide you and them in the wayes of right Juſtice, to give Judgment in the matters and cauſes aforeſaid, who are or may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in be concerned.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the people and worſhippers of God, own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and allowed by the Liturgie of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SEeing that meeting together upon the account of Religion and Worſhip of God, contrary to what is allowed by the Liturgie, or practiſe of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> to the number of five or above, is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted an offence, puniſhable with Impriſonment, and Tranſportation, by the late Act; it is very good to take notice, and that all Jurors, Judges, and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Law, as well as Witneſſes, do conſider who are the only perſons and people owned and allowed of by the Liturgie, as the people and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers of him, that ſuch may not be puniſhed upon ſuch an account, but clearly acquitted from the force of the Penalties concerning the ſame.</p>
               <p n="1">1. They who are owned and allowed by the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgie as the people of God, and worſhippers of him,<note place="margin">Publick Baptiſm</note>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:42053:13"/>are ſuch as God the Father, through the Son of his love, hath out of his bounteous mercy granted that thing unto, which by Nature they could not have, that is to ſay, Regeneration, the work of his Spirit.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They who are Regenerated, and by that Act of Regeneration are grafted into the Body of Chriſts Congregation, which is holy, and declared ſo to be by the Liturgie.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They whom God, the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, hath been pleaſed both to Regenerate with his holy Spirit,<note place="margin">Publ. Bapt</note> and to receive them for his own chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren by Adoption, and to incorporate into his holy Congregation, are the worſhippers and people of God, owned and allowed by the Liturgie of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and therefore they may meet and aſſemble together upon the account of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, according to the allowance of the Liturgie.</p>
               <p n="4">4. They who being buryed with Chriſt in his death,<note place="margin">Publ. Bapt</note> are dead unto ſin, and do live unto righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and are made partakers of the Reſurrection of Chriſt, they are the people of God, and allowed by the Liturgie, as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p n="5">5. They in whom the old <hi>Adam</hi> is buried, and in whom the new Man is raiſed up,<note place="margin">Publ. Bapt</note> in whom all carnal affections do die, and all things belonging to the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit do live in them, and grow, are the people of God allowed by the Liturgie ſo to be, and may meet upon the account of Religion and Worſhip of God, to the number of five and above.</p>
               <p n="6">6. They who have ſpiritual power and ſtrength from the Lord, and Victory to tryumph againſt the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:42053:13"/>Devil, the World, and the Fleſh,<note place="margin">Publ. Bapt</note> and are endued with heavenly vertues, and are made Members of Chriſt, and Inheritors of the Kingdom of Heaven, thoſe are the Worſhippers and people of God allowed by the Liturgie, as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p n="7">7. They who are (not viciouſly, but) vertuouſly brought up, to lead a godly and a Chriſtian life, who following the example of Chriſt, and to be made like unto him,<note place="margin">See the latter end of publick Baptiſm, and that called the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on feaſt of Trinity only.</note> that as he died and roſe again for them, ſo they ſhould die from ſin, and riſe again unto righteouſneſs, who do continually mortifie in them all evil and corrupt Affections, and do daily proceed in all vertue and godlineſs of living, thoſe are the people allowed and owned by the Liturgie, who may meet and aſſemble together to perform duty and ſervice to God, at any time, and in any place, which is very meet, right, and their bounden duty, and that according to the Liturgie. See Publick Baptiſm, and Communion upon the Feaſt of Trinity.</p>
               <p n="8">8. They who are the ſervants of the ever-living God, who are regenerated by him, to whom he hath granted forgivneſs of all their ſins,<note place="margin">See that called con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation or laying on of hands.</note> and doth ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then them with the holy Ghoſt the <hi>Comforter,</hi> and doth alſo daily encreaſe in them his manifold Gifts of Grace, the Spirit of wiſdom &amp; underſtanding, the Spirit of counſel and heavenly ſtrength, the Spirit of knowledge and true godlineſs, and are filled with the Spirit of Gods holy fear, thoſe are the people and worſhippers of God, owned and allowed by the Liturgie, as aforeſaid; and they may meet and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble together in the way of the Worſhip of God,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:42053:14"/>and ought not for ſo doing to be impriſoned or ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, but acquitted and freed therefrom.</p>
               <p n="9">
                  <note place="margin">Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of hands.</note>9. They whom Almighty God doth make both to will and to do thoſe things that be good and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable unto him, who are defended with Gods heavenly Grace, that they may continue his children and people for ever: And do daily encreaſe in his holy Spirit, to whom God doth certifie (after the example of his holy Apoſtles) and aſſure them of his favour and goodneſs towards them, whoſe fatherly hand is over them, and his holy Spirit is ever with them, to lead them in the knowledg and obedience of his Word, thoſe are the people and Worſhippers of God, owned and allowed by the Liturgie, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid.</p>
               <p n="10">10. They to whom Almighty God giveth grace, to caſt away the works of darkneſs, and put on the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of light in the time of this mortal life,<note place="margin">Firſt Sund. in Advent. the Collect</note> &amp; they who in obedience to, and by vertue of the grace of God given and received, do caſt off the works of darkneſs, and put on the Armour of light in the time of this mortal life, are the people and worſhippers of God, owned, and ſo to be allowed by the Liturgie of the Church of <hi>England:</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. They to whom God doth grant and give hearts to learn to love their enemies &amp; have learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that Leſſon,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>S. Stephens</hi> day, the Collect.</note> as his bleſſed M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rtyr <hi>Stephen</hi> did, who prayed for his perſecutors, thoſe are the people of God owned and allowed by the Liturgie, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid.</p>
               <p n="12">12. They to whom God hath granted the true
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:42053:14"/>Circumciſion of the Spirit,<note place="margin">The Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion of Chriſt, the Coll.</note> whoſe hearts and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers are mortified from all worldly and carnal luſts, who do in all things obey Gods bleſſed Will, through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, thoſe are the people of God allowed by the Liturgie, to aſſemble and meet toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to perform duty and ſervice to God in the way of his Worſhip, as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p n="13">
                  <note place="margin">5. Sunday after Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phany, the Collect.</note>13. They who are the Church of God, are the Houſhold of God, but wicked and unſanctified peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are not ſo, becauſe the whole Body of the Church is governed and ſanctified by the Spirit of God: And it is the work of God to keep his houſhold and family, the Church,<note place="margin">Good Fri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>day (ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led) the Collects.</note> ſo governed and ſanctified con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually in his true Religion, who are defended by his mighty power, and ſuch may meet together in the way and Worſhip of God, being allowed by the Liturgie, as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p n="14">14. They whom the Lord teacheth, that all their doings without charity are nothing worth,<note place="margin">Quinqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge. Sund. Collect.</note> into whoſe hearts God doth pour that moſt excellent gift of Charity, the very bond of all peace and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, without which whoſoever liveth is counted dead before the Lord, thoſe are the people alſo who are owned &amp; allowed by the Liturgie of the Church of <hi>England. Quinquageſſima Sunday Collect.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="15">15. They who put away the Leven of malice and wickedneſs,<note place="margin">See Tueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day in Eaſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er week. the Coll. 3. Sunday after Eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, the Col.</note> that they may alwayes ſerve the Lord in pureneſs of living and truth, and being admitted into Chriſts Religion, do eſchew thoſe things that be contrary to their profeſſion (as the <hi>Quakers</hi> do) and follow all ſuch things as be agreeable to the ſame,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:42053:15"/>through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, thoſe people are owned and allowed by the Liturgie, as aforeſaid. <hi>Third Sunday after Eaſter Collect.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="16">16. They who own,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Sunday after Eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, the Col.</note> and have received and are led by that pure ſpiritual ſoul-ſaving juſtifying light which God is the Author of, by whom it's diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and made manifeſt to all men, whilſt they are in error, to lead them out of errors and the way of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs, into the way of righteouſneſs, which is the way of the Lord, they are the people owned and allowed by the Liturgie, as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p n="17">17. They who by the holy inſpiration and opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gods holy Spirit are made to think and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form that which is good,<note place="margin">The 4 <hi>&amp;</hi> 5 Sundays after Eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, the Col.</note> acceptable and well-plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to the Lord, who makes the minds of all faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful men to be of one Will, thoſe people, and their godly religious Meetings are owned and allowed by the Liturgie, as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p n="18">18. They whoſe hearts God hath taught by the light of his holy Spirit,<note place="margin">Whitſund. the Coli.</note> to whom by his Spirit he doth give and grant a right Judgment in all things, and evermore to rejoyce in his holy Comfort, thoſe peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and their godly meetings are owned and allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Liturgie of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="19">19. They who are protected,<note place="margin">4 Sunday after Trin. Coll. 1 Sunday after Trin. Coll. 5 Sunday after Trin. Coll.</note> ruled, and guided by the Lord, who is the ſtrength of all them that truſt in him, under whoſe government the courſe of this world may be peaceably ordered, that his Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions may joyfully ſerve him in all godly quietneſs, are owned and allowed by the Liturgie, as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p n="20">20. They who give, grant and allow of liberty of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:42053:15"/>Conſcience (to the people of God) in poynt of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Worſhip of God, are owned and allowed by the Liturgie; becauſe the Liturgie allows of the ſame, ſaying, that the ſervice of God is perfect free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,<note place="margin">2 Coll. for peace.</note> and becauſe the ſervice of God is perfect free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, none ought to be forced either to it or from it (contrary to the principle of God) by outward compulſion.</p>
               <p n="21">21. They who have received the grace and gift of God, whereby their fleſh is ſubdued to the Spirit,<note place="margin">1 Sunday in Lent, the Coll.</note> by vertue whereof they may ever, and alwayes obey the godly motions of the Spirit of God in righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and true holineſs,<note place="margin">And 2. Sunday in Lent, the Coll.</note> to the honour and glory of God, who have no power of themſelves to help themſelves, but are kept and defended both out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly in body, and inwardly in ſoul, from all ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities which may happen to the body, &amp; from all evil thoughts which may aſſault and hurt the ſoul; and that by the Spirit and power of the Almighty God, through Chriſt Jeſus the Son of his Love, thoſe are the people and worſhippers of God, and both they, and their godly religious Meetings are owned by the Lord, and allowed by the Liturgie of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> are not therefore puniſhable by the late Act on that account, as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p n="22">22. They who have obtained of the God of all mercy perfect remiſſion and forgiveneſs of ſins,<note place="margin">Firſt day of Lent. the Coll.</note> through Chriſt Jeſus, in whom God hath by his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rit and power made new and contrite hearts, who by the goodneſs of Almighty God, are, or may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved evermore, both in body and ſoul, through
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:42053:16"/>Chriſt Jeſus the Son of his Love, thoſe are the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and worſhippers of God,<note place="margin">5 Sunday in Lent Coll.</note> and both they and their godly religious Meetings are owned by the Lord, and allowed by the Liturgie, as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p n="23">23. They who through the tender love and mercy of the Lord do follow the example of Chriſt, in his great humility and patience, and are made partakers of his reſurrection,<note place="margin">Sunday next be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Eaſter the Coll.</note> who are governed and ſanctified by the Spirit of God, of whom the Lord receives ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications and prayers, which they offer before him, for all eſtates of men,<note place="margin">Good Frid Collects.</note> in his holy Congregation, which is ſo governed and ſanctified by the Spirit of God, as aforeſaid, thoſe are the people which God doth own as his worſhippers, and both they and their godly Meetings are owned and allowed by the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgie of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> and therefore they ought neither to be impriſoned nor baniſhed for ſo doing, but rather to be freed and clearly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitted from all Eccleſiaſtical cenſures, and temporal puniſhments concerning the ſame.</p>
               <p n="24">24. They unto whom God hath granted, and doth or may grant his holy Spirit, alwayes to think and do ſuch things as be right and good in the ſight of God, ſo that they which cannot be without him,<note place="margin">9 Sunday after Trin. Collect.</note> may by him be able to live according to his Will in all things, are the people owned and allowed by the Liturgie, ſo that the people of God are enabled by the Spirit given unto them of God, to do and perform that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies which is acceptable and according to the Will of God, as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p n="25">25. They are the people of God, and allowed by
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:42053:16"/>the Liturgie of the Church of <hi>England,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">7 Sunday after Trin. Coll.</note> in whoſe hearts the Lord God of all power and might, who is the Author and giver of all good things, doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graff the love of his name, and doth encreaſe in their hearts his true Religion, and doth alſo nouriſh them with all goodneſs, who of his great mercy doth keep them in the ſame, through Chriſt Jeſus our Lord: ſo that the people of God have the love of God en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grafted in them, and true religion is planted within them, and doth encreaſe in their hearts, who are nouriſhed with the vertue and goodneſs of God, and by his power preſerved and kept in the ſame; and who more in that than the <hi>Quakers,</hi> ſo called? Conſider well of it, and do not unworthily puniſh them, for being ſo owned and allowed of both in principle, practiſe, and judgment or doctrine, by the Liturgie, as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p n="26">26. They are the people allowed by the Liturgie,<note place="margin">12 Sunday after Trin. Coll.</note> whom God almighty and everlaſting is alwayes rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to hear, and on whom he poureth down abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of mercy, forgiving them thoſe things where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of Conſcience is afraid, ſo that Conſcience is afraid, until God out of his mercy forgive ſins and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, and do reſtore Conſcience into a capacity again of becoming the ſervant of God;<note place="margin">13 Sunday after Trin. Coll.</note> therefore it is by the only gift of God, that his true and faithful people do perform him true and laudable ſervice, and they are the true and faithful people and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers of God, who by the only gift of God do per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form him true and laudable ſervice, as aforeſaid; and ſuch people, and their godly religious Meetings
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:42053:17"/>and Exerciſes,<note place="margin">On S <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> day the Coll.</note> are owned by the Lord, and allowed by the Liturgie of the Church, therefore ſuch ought not to be puniſhed by Impriſonment or baniſhment for ſerving God according to the gift of God.</p>
               <p n="27">27. They to whom God the Father, by his Son Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, hath given, or doth give many excellent gifts, and commandeth them to feed his Flock, are to be diligent in preaching Gods holy Word, and the people to whom it is ſo preached, who do obedient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly follow the ſame, are Miniſters and people of God; and the people of God are to ſerve God according to the gift of God (allowed by the Liturgie) and they are the true &amp; faithful people of God, in whoſe hearts his love is engrafted, true Religion planted, and doth encreaſe in their hearts, who are nouriſhed with the vertue and goodneſs of God, and by his power are preſerved and kept in the ſame, who by the gift of God do perform true and laudable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice unto God, as aforeſaid; and as that is owned and allowed by the Liturgie, ſo likewiſe by the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture; and doth not therefore both Liturgie and Scripture own and allow of the Doctrines, Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and practiſes of the people of God, reproachful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called <hi>Quakers,</hi> and others?</p>
               <p n="28">28. For the Scripture ſaith, <hi>As every man hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the gift, even ſo miniſter the ſame one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as good Stewards of the manifold grace of God; If any man ſpeak, let him ſpeak as the Oracles of God; If any man miniſter, let him do it as of the ability which God giveth, that God in all things may be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified through Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> as it is written 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.11.</p>
               <p n="29">
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:42053:17"/>29. Whereby it may be obſerved, that none are enjoyned, commanded, or required of God to mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter from him to the ſouls of the people, but them to whom the gift of Miniſtration is given; and alſo, that all are commanded, enjoyned, and required by the Lord to Miniſter from him to the people, to whom the gift of Miniſtration is given, ſo that the Goſpel is to be preached with the Holy Ghoſt ſent down from Heaven, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.11, 12.</p>
               <p n="30">30. And as it is evident, and remains true, that the Miniſters of the Goſpel of Chriſt, are by a ſpiritual power and Goſpel authority,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.10, 11. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.11, 12. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.1, 2 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1, 2 <hi>Act.</hi>
                  </note> whereby they are to be commended in the ſight of God to the Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of thoſe that receives them, as Miniſters of the Goſpel of Chriſt, to whom the gift of Miniſtration is given of God for that end and purpoſe, to convert people from the evil of their wayes and doings, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, by turning them from darkneſs unto light, and ſo from the power of Satan unto God, they are to preach in the Spirit, and to the ſpirits in priſon, with the Holy Ghoſt ſent down from Heaven.</p>
               <p n="31">31. So are both Miniſters and people to pray unto God, and praiſe him in the Spirit, and that accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Apoſtolick doctrine, as it is written <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.14. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26, 27. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.15.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, By what hath been ſaid, it is evident, and doth appear what perſons and Meetings are owned and allowed both by the Liturgie and Scripture, and that by the allowance of both, the ſervice and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God is to be performed by the Spirit and gift of God: And that they who meet, preach, and pray,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:42053:18"/>or perform duty and ſervice to God in the Spirit, and by the gift of God, they are the only people owned by the Lord, as his people, and worſhippers of him, and alſo allowed by the Liturgie, as aforeſaid. Therefore the people of God called <hi>Quakers,</hi> and others, who perform ſervice unto God by the gift of God, are owned and allowed by the Liturgie and Scripture, as aforeſaid, and ought to be acquitted from all Eccleſiaſtical Cenſures and Temporal pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments concerning the ſame.</p>
               <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:42053:18"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
